Guide to the Edward Maurice Cohart Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward Maurice Cohart papers
1936-1978
MS 1319
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.75
(15 boxes)
The papers consist of office files and course material which document Edward M. Cohart's career as professor of public health. There is extensive material for two major projects: the development of a Cancer Control Program at Yale and a research project of time studies of public health personnel. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Cohart, Edward
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were accessioned from the Department of Epidemiology and Public Health, ca. 1971. Gift of Mary Cohart, 1995.
Scope and Contents
The Edward M. Cohart Papers consist of office files from the early part of his career as a professor of public health at Yale. They document his two major projects: the development of a Cancer Control Program at Yale, and a research project consisting of time studies of public health personnel. The Cancer Control Program approached cancer as a public health problem, to be dealt with on a community basis. The program involved both cancer research and special training for various types of public health workers. The personnel research project, co-directed by William R. Willard, used time studies to determine the content and requirements of public health jobs. The project studied 1648 people in six states. Both of these projects were supported by grants from the United States Public Health Service.
The office files consist of correspondence, writings, reports, research materials, samples of questionnaires and other forms from the personnel research project, grant materials and printed matter. They have been arranged in a single alphabetical sequence, by name of correspondent or by type of material. The central working files for the projects described above will be found under the headings "Yale Public Health Personnel Research Project" and "Yale University School of Medicine. Department of Public Health: Cancer Control Program," but most of the other papers also concern these two projects. There are two folders of correspondence with Ira V. Hiscock, the chairman of the Yale Department of Public Health during this period, but most of the exchanges concern routine departmental matters.
The papers were accessioned from the Department of Epidemiology and Public Health, ca. 1971.
Biographical / Historical
Edward Maurice Cohart was born in 1909. He received a B.A. degree from Columbia University in 1928 and a M.D. in 1933. Cohart was in private practice from 1935-1942. He received a M.P.H. degree in 1947, and was a cancer control consultant for the United States Public Health Service from 1947-1948. Cohart was an associate professor of public health at Yale University from 1948-1956, a professor of public health from 1956-1960, and the C.-E.A. Winslow Professor of Public Health from 1960-1978.
EDWARD MAURICE COHART, 1909 -
1909 born in Brooklyn, N. Y.; son of Maurice Abraham and Emma (Chess) Cohart
1928 received B. A. from Columbia University
1933 received M. D.
1933 married Mary Schleifer
1935-1942 in private practice
1947 received M. P. H.
1947-1948 cancer control consultant, United States Public Health Service
1948-1956 Associate professor of public health, Yale University
1955-1956 Deputy commissioner of Department of Health, New York City; also consultant in public health at Institute of Public Administration, N. Y.
1956 received Honorary M. A. from Yale University
1956-1960 Professor of public health, Yale University
1960-1978 Charles-Edward A. Winslow Professor of Public Health, Yale University
1961 Acting chairman, Department of Public Health, Yale University
1965-1968 Secretary-Treasurer, Association of Schools of Public Health
1966-1967 President, New England Public Health Association
1966-1968 Chairman, Department of Epidemiology and Public Health, Yale University,
1978 Charles-Edward A. Winslow Professor Emeritus of Public Health, Yale University
-from Who's Who in America, 40th ed., 1978-1979, p. 635; Historical Register of Yale University, 1951-1968, p. 219
Arrangement
Arranged by inventory and additional material.
Cancer -- Research; Public health -- Study and teaching; Public health; Time study; Educators; Physicians; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Cohart, Edward; Hiscock, Ira V. (Ira Vaughan), 1892-; Yale Public Health Personnel Research Project; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Dept. of Public Health. Cancer Control Program
- Inventory, 1936-(1947-1958); 4.75 linear feet (12 boxes)
  - American Cancer Society, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Heart Association, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American National Red Cross, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - American Public Health Association, 1947-1951, 1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General note
    see also: box 5, folder 45-46
  - Clippings, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Connecticut Cancer Society
    - General, 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Film attendance lists, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Connecticut Health League, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Connecticut Public Health Association, 1954-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Connecticut State Department of Health
    See: box 4, folder 44
  - Correspondence, general, 1948-1950 October (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Correspondence, general, 1950 November - 1954 October (Box 2, Folder 14-22)
  - Correspondence, general, 1954 November--1955, undated (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
  - Correspondence re: reprints, 1948-1955, undated (Box 3, Folder 26-29)
  - Council of Social Agencies, 1949-1951, 1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 30-31)
  - Fairfield Health Department, Fairfield, Connecticut, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Fairfield Visiting Nurse Association, Fairfield, Connecticut, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital: Rooming-in Time Study Committee, 1949-1953, undated (Box 4, Folder 33-35)
  - Harvard School of Public Health, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Hiscock, Ira V., 1948-1955 (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
  - Knapp, Margaret, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Massachusetts Department of Public Health, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - National Cancer Institute, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    See also: box 5, folder 45-46
  - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - National Health Council, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - National Tuberculosis Association, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
  - New Haven Cancer Society
    see: box 1 folder 6
  - New York Academy of Medicine, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Pollack, Earl S., 1950 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Public Administration Service, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Public Health Cancer Association of America, 1948-1952 (Box 5, Folder 45-46)
  - Public Health Reports, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - U. S. Public Health Service
    - General, 1949-1952 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Grants, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 49)
      General
      See also: box 4, folder 41
  - University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Writings by Cohart, 1936-1954, undated (Box 5, Folder 51-55)
  - Yale Alumni in Public Health, 1948-1951 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Yale Medical Society, 1948-1951 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Yale Public Health Personnel Research Project
    - Reports, 1952-1954 (Box 6, Folder 57-61)
    - Administrative, general, 1950-1955, undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Correspondence, general, 1950-1951 August (Box 6, Folder 63-64)
    - Correspondence, general, 1951 September - 1955, undated (Box 7, Folder 65-67)
    - Grant materials, 1948-1954, undated (Box 7, Folder 68-72)
    - Hiscock, Irene Gilbert, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Hiscock, William McConway, 1950-1955, undated (Box 7, Folder 73-75)
    - Job candidates: D-S, 1950 (Box 7, Folder 76-79)
    - Job candidates: T-Y, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Project Operations, 1950-1952, undated (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Sample posting sheets, 3x5" slips, code sheets, 1951-1952, undated (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Willard, William R., 1951-1955, undated (Box 8, Folder 83-84)
    - Wyatt, Laurence Reginald, 1950-1952, undated (Box 8, Folder 85-86)
    - Wyatt, Muriel Ann, 1950-1952, undated (Box 8, Folder 86)
      See also: box 5, folder 47
  - Yale University School of Medicine
    - Administrative, general, 1948-1949, 1955, undated (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Atypical Growth Research Unit, 1950-1951 (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Clinical Sciences Committee, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Curriculum Committee, 1953, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Department of Public Health
      - Administrative, general, 1948-1949, 1953-1955, undated (Box 9, Folder 90)
      - Cancer Control Program, 1948-1950 April (Box 9, Folder 91-96)
      - Cancer Control Program, 1950 May - 1954 (Box 10, Folder 97-107)
      - Cancer Control Program: grant materials, 1947-1954 June (Box 10, Folder 108-113)
      - Committee on Essays, [1946?], 1948-1951, undated (Box 11, Folder 114)
      - Course materials: Biostatistics, 1949-1950, undated (Box 11, Folder 115)
      - Course materials: cancer: miscellaneous, [ca. 1944-1950],[1955?] undated (Box 11, Folder 116)
        See also: box 10, folder 108-113
      - Course materials: cancer nursing, 1948-1949, undated (Box 11, Folder 117)
      - Course materials: preventive medicine and public health, [1951?], 1952 (Box 11, Folder 117)
      - Course materials: principles and practices of public health, [ca. (Box 11, Folder 118)
      - Course materials: miscellaneous, 1951, undated (Box 11, Folder 119)
      - Curriculum, 1948-1951, undated (Box 12, Folder 120-121)
        See also: box 10 folder 108-113
      - Curriculum: term schedules, 1948-1953, undated (Box 12, Folder 122)
      - Personnel, 1948-1951, undated (Box 12, Folder 123)
      - Research projects, 1950, undated (Box 12, Folder 123)
      - Seminars, Journal Club, 1947-1951, undated (Box 12, Folder 124-125)
      - Staff meetings: minutes, 1948-1950, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 126-127)
      - Students: lists, memos, correspondence, prospectuses, 1948-1951, 1954-1955, undated (Box 12, Folder 128-129)
      - Toxicology seminars: notices, 1950-1951 (Box 12, Folder 130)
        See also: box 12, folder 131
      - Tumor conferences: notices, 1950-1951 (Box 12, Folder 130)
        See also: box 4, folder 37-38
    - Institute of Occupational Medicine and, 1948-1950, undated (Box 12, Folder 131)
- Additional Material, Circa 1950-1978; Accession 1995-M-138; 3 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Received From: Mary Schleifer Cohart, 1995 April 25
  - Personal and university files, Circa 1950-1978 (Box 1)
  - Course material, Circa 1950-1978 (Box 2)
  - Course material, Circa 1950-1978 (Box 3)